Guide to the James T. Sears Papers, 1918-2011 and undated, bulk 1950-2004 RL.01162
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Research and Writings, 1941-2007 and undated, bulk 1975-2005, 176 boxes
  - Major Works Subseries, 1941-2007 and undated, 104 boxes
    - Lonely Hunters: an Oral History of Lesbian and Gay Southern Life, 1948-1968 (1997), 1954-1998 and undated, 10 boxes
      - Research Files, 1954-1996 and undated
        - Growing up as a Jewish Lesbian, 1997-1998 (Chapter in Generations of Youth..., 1998; became a chapter in Lonely Hunters) (Box 87A)
        - Hall, Gordon Langley: clippings, 1963, 1989, and 1993 (Box 87A)
        - Hall material from Perkins Library, 1963-1972 (Box 87A)
        - Miami juvenile delinquency hearing, 1954-1955 (Box 87A)
        - Nichols, Jack: notes for memoirs, 1995-1996 (Box 87B)
        - Nichols, Jack: correspondence with Sears, and early materials (correspondence, writings, and clippings), 1963-1996 and undated (Box 87B)
        - Notes, undated (Box 87B)
        - Pages from Dialectics chapter; writings by Lige Clark and Jack Nichols, 1996 (Box 87B)
        - Penelope, Julia, 1996 (Box 87B)
        - Related fifties articles, 1959-1964, 1989 (Box 88)
          Chiefly reprints of early gay magazines Janus and One, but also reading lists of gay sci-fi and list of gay pulp fiction at Special Collections Library, Duke.
        - Research aids from Special Collections Library, Duke University (subject bibliographies, primary source lists), 1995-1996 (Box 88)
        - Simmons, Dawn Langley: correspondence and clippings (contains photographic material), 1995-1996 (Box 88)
        - Sponnoble correspondence and notes, 1995-1996 (Box 88)
        - Johns Committee files [University of Florida legal case], 1957-1966 and undated (Box 89-92)
          [Box 91 contains photographic materials.]
    - Rebels, Rubyfruit, and Rhinestones: Queering Space in the Stonewall South (2001), 1950s-2005 and undated, 56 boxes
      Arranged into the following subseries: Administrative Files, Correspondence, Drafts and Proofs, Publicity, and Research Files. These divisions and their internal arrangement are further described below. The largest group, the research files (36 boxes), documents Sears' work on the book through correspondence, clippings and articles files, interviews, memoirs, oral histories, regional material from southern states, files on activist groups, memorabilia, and other material. The research files also house a set of diaries written by a gay youth from 1973-1993, and a large component of materials, chiefly correspondence, written by Jack Nichols and Lige Clarke. Other material on Nichols can be found in the Jack Nichols Papers Series.
      - Administrative Files, 1994-2005, 3 folders
        - Consent forms, 1996-2005, 2 folders (Box 93)
        - Duke University consent forms, 1994-2000 (Box 93)
      - Correspondence, 1994-2001, 5 boxes
        Consists of correspondence between Sears and various contacts related to the project. Organized in two sections: alphabetical order by recipient, and editorial and location-specific correspondence. The second section is arranged in order as received.
        - A-C, 26 folders (Box 93)
        - C-J, 30 folders (Box 94)
        - J-N, 26 folders (Box 95)
        - N-W, 39 folders (Box 96)
        - W-Z, 10 folders (Box 97)
        - Editorial, 2000 (Box 97)
        - Promotional blurbs, 2000-2001 (Box 97)
        - Rutgers, 1997-2000, 2 folders (Box 97)
        - Photo contacts, 1999-2000 (Box 97)
        - City contacts, 18 folders (Box 97)
      - Drafts and Proofs, 1998-2001, 5 boxes
        - 5 boxes (Box 98-102)
      - Publicity, 2000-2001, 3 folders
        Includes correspondence, flyers, and travel plans for publicity tours as well as press reviews of the book.
        - 3 files (Box 102)
      - Research Files, 1950s-2001, 46 boxes
        Contains a large amount of research materials pertaining to the writing of Rebels, Rubyfruit, and Rhinestones, including correspondence between third parties, clippings, gay newspaper issues, chapters of books consulted by Sears, flyers, programs, newsletters, diaries, oral histories, promotional materials, minutes, and memorabilia. The subseries is organized into rough subject areas with titles originally assigned by Sears, with individual folders left largely in the original order as received. These subject areas are organized alphabetically within the subseries and their contents are further described below. Many of the folders carry state names, and contain research materials gathered by Sears in the southern U.S. Extensive additional materials on Jack Nichols and Lige Clarke can be found in the Jack Nichols Papers Series in this collection.
        - 1970s Articles, 14 folders (Box 103)
          Principally popular and academic articles and book chapters by others, providing a general background on social issues of the 1970s.
        - 1970s articles, 11 folders (Box 104)
        - Other 1970s material (Box 104)
        - 1980s, 11 folders (Box 104)
          A mixture of material including bibliographies, newspaper articles, and a large group of individually foldered flyers, pamphlets, catalogues, and other material from gay and lesbian organizations from the 1980s.
        - 1980s, 5 folders (Box 105)
        - 1980s organization material, 49 folders (Box 105)
        - 1980s organization material, 69 folders (Box 106)
        - Activist groups, 1960s-1980s, 4 folders (Box 106)
          Material related to various political and social activist groups active in the 1960s, 1970s, and 1980s. Includes newspapers, newsletters, flyers, posters, correspondence, and other materials. Subjects include the Student Southern Organizing Committee, the North American Bioregional Conference, the People's Party, the North American Congress of Homophile Organizations, the Gay Rights Lobby, the National Gay Task Force, and the Gay Sex Alliance.
        - Activist groups, 13 folders (Box 107)
        - Activist groups, 6 folders (Box 108)
        - AIDS and other medical materials, 1970s-1980s, 10 folders (Box 108)
          Mostly newspaper and magazine articles about the AIDS epidemic, but also includes material on sexually transmitted diseases and materials from the Gay Caucus of the American Psychiatric Association.
        - Timothy Bass diaries, 1977-1993, 8 folders (Box 109)
        - Biker clubs, 1972-1980, undated, 3 folders (Box 110)
        - Logan Carter, 1970s-1980s, and undated, 6 folders (Box 110)
          Documents from the life of Logan Carter/Roxanne Russell. Includes newspaper articles, diaries, book manuscripts, and correspence with Jack Nichols.
        - Lige Clarke and Jack Nichols correspondence, 1967, 3 folders (Box 110)
        - Lige Clarke and Jack Nichols correspondence, 1967-1968 (Box 111)
        - Lige Clarke and Jack Nichols correspondence, 1968-1988, and undated, 11 folders (Box 112)
        - Lige Clarke and Jack Nichols articles, circa 1974 (Box 112)
        - Lige Clarke and Jack Nichols articles, 1969-1973, 3 folders (Box 113)
        - Lige Clarke and Jack Nichols - Nichols writings about Clarke, 1970, 1975, 1998, and undated, 3 folders (Box 113)
        - Drag Queens, 1970s-1996 and undated, 10 folders (Box 113)
          [Original copies of audiocassettes closed to use. Technical Services staff must arrange to have use copy made on request. Please contact Research Services staff before coming to use the collection.]
        - Florida, 1970s-1980s, 5 folders (Box 113)
          Newspaper articles, biographical documents, FBI reports, legal documents, and other material from Florida. Topics include Jack Campbell's campaign for Miami Commissioner, the Miami equal treatment ordinance, and the Anita Bryant affair.
        - Florida, 1970s-1980s, 16 folders (Box 114)
        - Florida, 1977-1980, 1997, 2 folders (Box 115)
        - Georgia, 1970s-1997, 20 folders (Box 115)
          Includes material on Atlanta gay organizations and the Supreme Court's 1985 Bowers v. Hardwick sodomy case.
        - Georgia - ALFA, 1972-1991, 2 folders (Box 116)
        - Kentucky, 1950s-1990s, 26 folders (Box 116)
          Covers activities at the University of Kentucky and in Louisville, as well as the Sam Dorr case from 1982.
        - Peter Lee, correspondence and datebooks, 1950s-2000 (Box 117-119)
        - Lesbians, 1969-1996 (Box 120-121)
          Contains chiefly print material about lesbian and feminist figures, organizations, and issues, in the form of book chapters, biographical entries, newspaper articles, flyers, and pamphlets.
        - Louisiana, 1971-1982 (Box 122-123)
          Includes material on Gertrude Stein Society and the study "Hidden People."
        - Mississippi, 1969-1990s (Box 124)
          Includes articles about the 1983 gubernatorial election; letters, publications, minutes, and other material from the Mississippi Gay Allliance; and letters between "Eddie's Boys."
        - Mississippi, 1969-1990s, 14 folders (Box 125)
          Includes "Eddie's Boys" material.
        - Nichols, Jack, 1970s-1991, 2 folders (Box 125)
          Contains newspaper and magazine articles, manuscripts, speeches, interviews, correspondence, clippings, and other material created by Jack Nichols. See also the Jack Nichols Papers Series in this collection for extensive materials on Nichols and Lige Clark.
        - Jack Nichols material, 1960s-2003 and undated (Box 126-128)
          Contains many folders of correspondence (1990s-2003), newspaper and magazine articles, manuscripts, speeches, interviews, clippings, and other materials by and about Jack Nichols.
        - Jack Nichols, undated, 4 folders (Box 129)
        - Jack Nichols correspondence A-L, 1993-2003, 8 folders (Box 129)
        - Jack Nichols correspondence M-Z, 1988-2003, 9 folders (Box 130)
        - North Carolina, 1950s-1990s, 8 folders (Box 130)
          Mostly information and material on the history of gay groups in various North Carolina cities, as well as a large number of newspapers from the 1970s.
        - North Carolina, 1950s-1990s, 11 folders (Box 130)
          Chiefly information and material on the history of gay groups in various North Carolina cities, as well as a large number of newspapers from the 1970s.
        - North Carolina, 1969-2002, 31 folders (Box 131)
        - North Carolina, 1969-1985, 7 folders (Box 132)
        - North Carolina - The Protean, circa 1970 (Box 132)
        - Religion (Box 133-135)
        - Short Mountain (Tennessee), 1974-1995 and undated (Box 136-137)
          Minutes, correspondence, deeds, flyers, maps, notebooks, and other materials from the Short Mountain Sanctuary in Tennessee, an intentional community for gay men.
        - Short Mountain correspondence, 1980-1983, 2 folders (Box 136-137)
        - Short Mountain correspondence, 1980-1983 and undated (Box 138-139)
        - South Carolina, 1969-1998, 22 folders (Box 140)
          Chiefly material relating to South Carolina University in Columbia, SC, including letters, minutes, flyers, and newsletters of the Lambda Alliance.
        - Tennessee, 1969-1991, and undated, 23 folders (Box 141)
          Additional material about Tennessee, unrelated to Short Mountain, focusing on Memphis and various political campaigns.
        - Texas, 1967-1991 and undated (Box 142-144)
        - Virginia, 1977-1978, 3 folders (Box 144)
        - Virginia,1968-1984 (Box 145-146)
          [Contains microfilm titled Richmond gay history documents; may need to be reformatted before use. Please contact Research Services before coming to use this collection.]
          [Contains diskettes that need to be migrated before use. Please contact Research Services before coming to use this collection.]
        - Uncategorized material, 1960s-1980s, and undated, 2 boxes (Box 146-147)
          Research material of broad application. Topics include racism within the gay community; hate crimes and homophobia. Includes miscellaneous notes, publications, newspaper clippings, and other items.
        - Memorabilia, undated (Box 148)
          Bumper stickers, two t-shirts, a rainbow streamer, and two small boxes of pins and buttons.
      - Transcripts, 1978, 1996, and undated, 1 box
        Transcripts of interviews conducted by Sears and others, related to the book Rebels, Rubyfruit, and Rhinestones. Folders sorted in alphabetical order by interview subject's name.
        - Interview transcripts, 1978, 1996, and undated, 26 folders (Box 149)
    - Behind the Mask of the Mattachine: The Hal Call Chronicles and the Early Movement for Homosexual Emancipation (2006), 1918-2006 and undated, bulk 1950s-2006, 24 boxes
      Correspondence, writings, interview transcripts, administrative files, minutes, diaries, memoirs, printed materials, relating to the life of Hal Call, prominent member of the early gay rights movement, the history of the Mattachine Society with which Call was engaged, and the writing of Sears' book Behind the Mask of the Mattachine. Arranged in the following series: Administrative, Financial, and Legal Files; Hal Call Papers; Correspondence; Diaries, Memoirs, Yearbooks; Drafts; Interview Transcripts; Photographic Material; and Printed Material. The bulk of the personal papers of Hal Call date from the early 1940s to the 1970s and include correspondence, writings, diaries, and printed matter related to the early years of the gay liberation movement. See descriptions below for more detail on each group of materials.
      - Administrative, Financial, and Legal Files (Mattachine Society), 1953-1974 and undated
        A variety of materials that document the organization, meetings, conventions and various financial and legal activities of the Mattachine Society. Files are divided into alphabetical and chronological runs of folders. The alphabetical folders reflect a broad range of topics, including all of the following: balance sheets and other budget activities; chapters of the Society in various cities; FBI files; related groups such as One, Inc. and Pan-Graphic Press; and the work of various committees, especially the Publications Committee. The chronological run of folders consists almost entirely of minutes, agendas, and related documents from meetings and conventions. This group of folders contains a mix of documents that were produced by individual chapters as well as national conventions of the Society, w/some individual folders containing items from multiple sources; all are interfiled chronologically.
        - Alphabetical: Adonis--Speeches, 1953-1974 and undated, 29 folders (Box 150)
        - Chronological: Meetings, Conventions, Minutes, and Related Documents (Box 151)
          - 1951-1960 and undated, 13 folders (Box 151)
          - 1954-1960 and undated, 15 folders (Box 152)
          - 1960-1964 and undated, 8 folders (Box 153)
      - Hal Call Papers, 1918-2000 and undated, bulk 1950s-2000
        - Correspondence, index to 1946-1950 (Box 153)
        - Correspondence, 1941-1972, 10 folders (Box 153)
        - Correspondence, 1950-2000 and undated, 13 folders (Box 154)
        - Diaries and yearbooks, 1940s, 1967-1998
          Consists of thirty years of Hal Call's yearbooks and appointment books in forty-five volumes, plus an undated World War II era notebook. Items contain a mix of appointments, lists of contacts, and brief day-to-day record-keeping for various financial transactions of the Mattachine Society.
          - 1940s, 1967-1980, 17 volumes (Box 155)
          - 1981-1990, 14 volumes (Box 156)
          - 1991-1998, 15 volumes (Box 157)
        - Interviews (transcripts) of Hal Call by various interviewers, 1980-2000, 10 folders (Box 158)
        - Photographic material, 1918-1996 and undated (Box 158)
        - Printed material, 1926-1999 and undated, 11 folders (Box 158)
        - Oversize Materials (Box 159)
          - Hal Call correspondence, 1945-1948, 5 items (Box 159)
          - Hal Call Papers printed materials, newspapers and clippings, 1931-1964 and undated, 7 folders (Box 159)
      - Correspondence, 1933-2006 and undated
        A mix of individual and organizational correspondence relating to the history of gay rights, the history of the Mattachine Society and its various chapters, and to Sears's research for his book. Individuals prominently represented, mainly in the early years, include Henry Gerber, Frank McCourt, and Manuel boyFrank. Organizational correspondence, heavily concentrated in the 1950s and early 1960s, includes: material about the early history of the Mattachine in San Francisco; some material from the New York chapter; and correspondence with other organizations such as ONE, Inc. and the Atheneum Society of American, Inc., the Florida activist group founded by Richard Inman. Finally, Sears's research correspondence, including some email, is filed at the end of this file set. Arranged chronogically.
        - Henry Gerber, Frank McCourt, Manuel boyFrank, and early Mattachine materials, 1933-1979 and undated, 11 folders (Box 160)
        - Mattachine materials from San Francisco and New York, 1950-1991 and undated, 42 folders (Box 161)
        - Mattachine materials from San Francisco and New York; ONE, Inc., 1957-1975 and undated, 29 folders (Box 162)
        - Mattachine materials; Richard Inman and Atheneum Society; James Sears correspondence and email, 1961-2006 and undated, 28 folders (Box 163)
      - Diaries, Memoirs, Yearbooks, 1968-1994
        Contains a variety of autobiographical documents for Jim Kepner and Prescott Townsend. Although the Kepner folders, as received, are labeled as diaries, they actually appear to be a typescript memoir written in the late 1980s or early 1990s. Arranged by author, then chronologically.
        - Kepner, Jim, diary, My First 66 Years of Gay Liberation, 1968-1990, 11 folders, typescript (Box 164)
        - Townsend, Prescott, Queer for Justice: an autobiographical memoir, (by Adrian Cathcart), 1994 (Box 164)
      - Drafts, 1919-2005 and undated, bulk 1999-2005
        Consists mainly of multiple drafts in typescript of various chapters of Behind the Mask of the Mattachine. At the beginning of these is a folder for Sears's 1999 proposal for the book, originally to be known as Calling Shots. At the end of the group are several folders of visual materials for the book, including photographs, clippings, and other printed materials. Since these items were numbered and thus possibly keyed to one or more drafts of the book, they were left in the current folder group rather than separated by format. Filed chronologically to the extent possible, but folder contents vary: most contain multiple drafts of a single chapter, but others contain a single draft of multiple chapters.
        - Proposal, 1999 (Box 165)
        - Drafts and introductions, 2001 June-2002 July (Box 165)
        - Chapters 1-10, various drafts, 2001 Aug.-2002 Jul., 12 folders (Box 165)
        - Chapters 11-28, various drafts, 2001 Dec.-2002 Sept., 16 folders (Box 166)
        - Chapters 1-36, various drafts, 2002 July-2004 Oct., 12 folders (Box 167)
        - Chapters 14-40, various drafts, 2004 May-2005 Aug., 6 folders (Box 168)
        - Visual materials for book, numbered 1-11, 21-50, 1919-1965 and undated, 8 folders (Box 168)
      - Interview Transcripts, 1962-2005 and undated
        Contains transcripts of interviews with over forty individuals that Sears conducted or gathered as part of his research for Behind the Mask of the Mattachine. Interviews conducted by Sears took place in the late 1990s and early 2000s, while those by other researchers took place as much as thirty years earlier up through the 1990s; other interviewers include Paul Cain, Martin Meeker, and Frank Prager. For most transcripts there are release forms signed by the interviewees; these are usually filed at the front of the folder containing the transcripts, but others were also left as received, in a separate folder at the beginning of the folder group. In addition to transcripts and release forms, folders also contain associated correspondence and e-mail between Sears, other researchers, and the interviewees; printed material; research notes; and a few photographs. Some folders contain only these supporting materials and no transcripts; they often appear to be preparatory work for interviews that did not take place. Interviews are mainly concerned with the Mattachine Society in San Francisco in the 1950s-1970s, but also cover chapters in other cities. Interviewees prominently cited in the book include: Martin Block, Ken Burns, Frank Kameny, Jim Kepner, Hal Lawson, Dorr Legg, Don Lucas, Phyllis Lyon, Del Martin, Jack Nichols, and Randy Wicker. Transcripts for several interviews with Hal Call are all housed in the Hal Call folder group in this subseries. Arranged alphabetically.
        - Interview release forms, Barker-Wicker, 2001-2004 (Box 169)
        - Transcripts, Anchor-Littlejohn, 1962-2005 and undated, 26 folders (Box 169)
        - Transcripts, Lucas-Wicker, 1956-2004 and undated, 20 folders (Box 170)
      - Photographic Materials, 1918-2000 and undated
        Contains 187 black-and-white prints, 25 color prints, 44 negatives, and circa 150 slides documenting three topics: the life of Hal Call; materials which may have been assembled by Call relating to an unidentified project on the history of gay erotica; and the early history of the Mattachine Society. The bulk of the materials relate to Hal Call and document his childhood, family, military service in World War II, work history, and include a variety of professional portraits and personal snapshots taken at different periods of his life. Separated by format, then arranged alphabetically by topic.
        - Hal Call--prints, slides, and negatives, 1918-2000 and undated, 5 folders and 1 box of slides (Box 171)
        - History of gay erotica--prints, slides, and negatives, circa 1960s-1970s and undated, 3 folders (Box 171)
        - Mattachine Society history--prints and slides, 1947 and undated, 2 folders (Box 171)
      - Printed Material, 1953-2006 and undated
        A variety of clippings, flyers, legal case histories, newsletters, photocopied articles, research about the history of erotica, and other printed materials. Consists mainly of documents generated by or about various chapters of the Mattachine Society in the 1960s and 1970s, but also includes research that Sears gathered in preparing his book. Newsletters from Chicago, Denver, Los Angeles, New York, and San Francisco form the largest category, comprising about a third of the materials gathered here. The Randy Wicker folders contain materials by and about Wicker. Arranged alphabetically, with folder titles derived from topical subjects, publication titles, and people's names.
        - Black Cat--Gerber/Hart Library, 22 folders (Box 172)
        - Gerber/Hart Library--Newsletters, Denver, 23 folders (Box 173)
        - Newsletters, Denver--The Rejected, 23 folders (Box 174)
        - Reprints--Vanguard, 15 folders (Box 175)
        - Wicker, Randy--Womack School, 12 folders (Box 176)
    - Edwin and John: A Personal History of the American South (2009), 1919-2008 and undated, bulk 1937-1959, 5 boxes